[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
invent your future at caci a national
security company revolutionizing
technology through digital c4 isr cyber
space engineering and i.t
transformations
you'll deliver information dominance
through the development of
next-generation solutions at caci you'll
be treated like the company's greatest
asset when a company believes their
people are their greatest asset they let
the best do what they do best
visit careers.caci.com
innovate to explore caci's engineering
and i.t opportunities
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host gavin henry and today my
guest is tim mcnamara
tim learned to program so he could
assist with humanitarian disasters
around the world from new zealand his
area of professional expertise is a
natural language processing and machine
learning tim's also the author of rust
in action an introduction to rust for
programmers who've never used a systems
programming language before he currently
works at tcdi and american legal
services and cyber security company as a
senior software architect tim welcome to
software engineering radio is there
anything i miss in your bio that you'd
like to add
no no no this covers it thanks very much
kevin so the goals for today's episode
on a rust 2021 edition
is to revisit ym when russ was created
because we did a show episode 279 with
florian gilcher i think on rust back in
2017 so that was four years ago so we're
also gonna learn to understand when to
use rust its top three benefits to
explore what's changed since our 2017
show and to understand what an addition
is and what the 2021 edition brings so
first question is the rust website
headline is a language empowering
everyone to build reliable and efficient
software
what does that mean
that's a
excellent place to start the rust
programming language is explicitly or at
least the community that surrounds the
rust programming language is explicitly
there to be able to support anyone
achieve their goals with software by the
safe and reliable aspect it's probably
the easiest one to
mentally grasp and that would be to say
that all things being equal your
application should use the least amount
of memory and the least amount of
compute resources in order to achieve
its aims so effectively rust is
attempting to eliminate waste
and
both in terms of compute resources but
also human resources we shouldn't
necessarily need to have security
vulnerabilities or
random crashes
you know our systems that we build these
software systems should actually be
stable and robust
and
that is sort of the technical side
of rust
now the empowering everything
is kind of this value-laden statement
that's intentionally there as a bit of a
jive i think at other language
communities and other open source
communities it's saying well actually
everyone is welcome
and
you shouldn't feel
that if you've only done javascript or
you've only done python or you've only
programmed in java that you
are not entitled to learn about
low-level high-performance software you
could definitely have a place in the
room we're trying to attract a very wide
spectrum of developers
so that the whole ecosystem supports
a better software industry a software
industry that's robust a software
industry that respects its users a
software industry that respects
programmers as a profession well i think
you've touched upon a few of my
follow-up questions so that was good can
you remind us why and when rust was
created for those that haven't listened
to the show in 2017
right so rust was originally made public
by mozilla so the organization had this
problem one is an existential crisis
which is chrome
came about and they tried to rapidly
enhance firefox in response in
particular the performance of this
javascript engine although the details
are probably somewhere in between but it
turns out that c plus plus is extremely
difficult to actually get working in a
very large team and there were
concurrency bugs there might be this
memory management kind of problems about
a classic
example is called a double free
where you might say that memory has been
freed and then some other part of the
program actually goes and tries to free
it again which is illegal behavior
another case and that rust
completely eliminates by design
is iterator invalidation so if you
change the array while you iterate
through it let's say you're adding or
removing items
this is like a source of really bad bugs
and
rust actually ensures that
that illegal or you know we might say
undefined behavior is completely
impossible
we have whole classes of bugs which just
don't exist in rust
and
therefore why rust was created was to
create a better c-plus plus it was there
to be able to enable very large systems
to be built with it
and
that involved creating a
productive and
relatively ergonomic language that
people who were not expert developers or
would never see themselves as sort of
expert systems programmers would still
be able to produce reasonable code and
possibly moreover they wouldn't be able
to accidentally insert massive security
vulnerabilities inside a very important
piece of software
does it do these checks and
optimizations on optimizations but lets
you know about all these things
when it's running or before it gets to
the point of being i presume it creates
a binary does it right so rust is a
compiled language
and therefore
the compiler has an opportunity to check
before
any program is actually run it turns out
that almost all of rust's safety checks
are actually checked at this compile
stage there's actually no runtime cost
at all to any of these safety features
what rust does is kind of tag data with
a lifetime just imagine we didn't have
any conditionals in our program we only
had a very linear way through
and you would know that let's say
variable a
could last from say step 10 through to
step 50.
and then for whatever reason after step
50 accessing that variable a was illegal
russ does that a similar kind of
analysis across the entire program
across every thread and it does it all
at compile time there are one or two
cases in which you will incur
a
runtime cost
so for example
if i try to access the ninth element of
an array or so if i look up an array by
by index
there will be a sort of what we call a
bounds check to say that the ninth
element actually exists
it is slightly possible to get around
that with high order programming
and in particular the functional
paradigm
and
you can mutate or perform
transformations on some data structure
with closures which are anonymous
functions
and
they are typically very heavily
optimized by the compiler and idiomatic
rust will often not require bounce
checking at all because it can guarantee
that it will only access safe and valid
memory
so there's certain ways to get around
that optimization
and safety there are a couple of
different styles of programming say an
imperative style with for loops and
accessing with an eye
you can imagine that you've created your
your index variable i and you're sort of
iterating from 0 through 10 rust doesn't
require you
to manually create an iterator like this
index variable that mode is available to
you
and sort of this mode of being very
imperative and it works but it's sort of
it's going against the grain slightly
and
the sort of idiomatic rust approach will
typically
be faster it's slightly more memory
efficient because it wouldn't require
the use of temporary variables
we've covered why and when rush was
created briefly when should a programmer
use rust
i don't want to speak for every
programmer but i can talk about when i
use rust so before rust i had basically
used python for about a decade and that
was my programming experience
and
i used rust where i sort of leaned
towards rust
when things were too slow is when i
turned to rust but actually now that i
am productive with it it's a
surprisingly versatile tool
i tend to kind of use it for command
line utilities and
all the way through to kind of network
services it's quite heavily used on the
back end of the web site so
for developing web apis is quite a
common use case as well
as this ability
for
rust to compile to the front end via a
technology called webassembly
rust also has a
special place to play inside embedded
programming it doesn't require an
operating system or an interpreter to
run
and so it can actually be compiled to
microcontrollers as well it can fit
in a very wide range of areas and where
i found it particularly useful
is data processing like high volumes
terabytes and more of mostly text data
but it does it very very quickly and it
uses very little memory and what sort of
companies people organizations are using
it
rust has been adopted by all of the
marquee tech companies the rust
foundation i think is sponsored by
at least
microsoft google facebook
huawei
the chinese tech company mozilla is
heavily involved
the best milestone would be 2015 as when
the 1.0 released
there was quite a lot of work prior to
that so i think the first public
announcement at all
was around
and or at least that may have been when
the the original developer grade and haw
actually started working on it there was
a long period where
the language itself was effectively
considered
unstable
where
rust wanted to be able to
if you think of its original use case
developing an alternative web browser
it was actually being developed in
lockstep with this big software project
and
they were molding the language to make
it more and more productive so there was
a very very long process of
developing language features or ripping
them out
or
inserting them
pre-stabilization
the milestone that matters is 2015. so
what it was getting thought about sort
of three years after go was coming
around i think 2005.
when they were both announced i think
rust may have been publicly announced
around 2012. rust and go look very
similar so they both had something that
looked very kind to go routines also
known as co-routines or lightweight
threads
and
the ability to kind of spawn
work
was baked into rust but that was
actually pulled away
pulled out of the language as it
stabilized and it became
a language that
became
much more aligned to
its peer languages predominantly c plus
and it took on a mantra of zero cost
abstractions that is that any
given
abstraction
should have
little to no runtime cost at all
and preferably no memory even so there
are quite a few things that are
available to you or
they look like types inside the rust
source code
then the compiler will actually
completely remove
inside the binary they purely exist as
the ability for you to
mold your program
as you'd like it but they don't actually
impose any runtime cost and they don't
have any runtime memory who is using it
i was doing some github action workflow
exploring last week and noticed all of
their containers that you can use and
git hub actions have rust pre-installed
so i thought that was a very good sign
but obviously
github is owned by microsoft so that
probably explains some of that so does
ross have a package manager
russ has an excellent package manager
cargo is its name and cargo is one of
the most fantastic pieces of software
that i've ever used and
i say that as someone who was always
terrified
whenever i was told that i needed to
compile a native extension
for some python package because you
would need a c
compiler and then you would always
encounter kind of weird linker issues
and
i
had no idea what i was doing
rust almost completely eliminates that
whole problem and
cargo just works it's ridiculous how
good it is it's almost
worth
using rust
just for cargo because it avoids you so
many problems
that's some statement isn't it it's
surprisingly valid
i mean coming from python where there's
like 16 different ways i i exaggerate
but of the setup tools there's just you
tools there's a whole bunch of other new
ones is it poetry is it pip is it uh you
know free and scientific programming is
it conda and then all of that
is
eliminated in rust and
it feels fresh i don't want to
evangelize too much but also just i keep
looking for the disillusionment with
rust every single tech thing that i get
excited about
after you know nine months say something
will just hit me and it'll just be
terrible and i'll look for the next
thing but the raster rust just keeps
getting better and better and better
and
yeah i'm just wrapped at the the ability
to be part of that story that's really
good to hear so now that we've had a
good introduction to rust let's start
exploring some of the top three benefits
on the rust website it says that rust
has performance
so let's talk about that in this section
how do we measure blazingly fast which
is one of the claims
that is one of the claims so the claim
is that rust will run
blazingly fast
and
that statement is
kind of paired up with with a notion of
called a garbage collector and a garbage
collector is a piece of software that
runs alongside your application if
you're running a java app or anything on
the clr so if you're in the dot net
ecosystem
or if you are a python programmer or
javascript programmer or a go programmer
you'll have a little utility that's kind
of bolted onto your application it's
managing memory
and requests for memory from the
operating system on your behalf
it takes time to run
and in some cases in fact many cases it
will actually halt the execution of your
program so that it could do its own work
and then very quickly swap that will
turn itself off and give your program
access to the cpu rust does not
need a garbage collector
every single
allocation of memory is actually defined
at compile time
but unlike say c or z plus plus
you never have to manually request it
the compiler understands exactly when
every single element of memory is
required it will only
access exactly what is being run we
touched it initially in the introduction
about
most things being done at compile time
where all the safety checks and memory
and tracking and
looking at how things going to go so
let's just take an example where we've
got a data structure that comes in over
the network but we don't know
what's going to be in it the size wise
how do you deal with the memory and
efficiency and predictive performance
when you've got unknowns from users
how does rust do that bit
rust will
give you a
couple of options it provides you with
the ability to say manually that i only
want say four megabytes of
ram available to
this incoming string or this incoming
stream of bytes
it provides you with the ability perhaps
to say that you can just process them on
the fly as they come in
otherwise it also gives you kind of
tools to be able to say that
you can use as much memory as needed
and so
the
language itself
is going to try to provide you with
the
tools
for you to kind of make the decision as
the programmer it's going to try to not
impose
its own will on you in terms of that
particular use case it doesn't make any
sense yeah i think so
the way
rust has been explained to
make the best choices for all this stuff
so you don't have to worry about
memory management and wait for the
garbage collector
and they're always getting better a year
but it sounds as if
if you do know what you're doing you can
help ross make his decision
something makes sense
right i think it does let's say that i
wanted to accept an http post request
so someone is submitting a form and we
don't know how long the form is but we
want to guard
the server that is hosting the
application
from being overrun with data
the thing that's most likely to happen
is that you will read in
only the amount that is required so it
might be one form element
and then that will be processed the web
framework itself you will probably have
a guard in there which says that once
i've hit say two megabytes or whichever
limit that you've provided that actually
the client will be cut off
the framework will return like
the too large response
in terms of say tcp
or sort of raw tcp the similar thing
might happen
try to understand if there's no run time
and no garbage collection
in the build process the compilation
how does it know
you know to handle a variable
memory requirement that's what i'm
trying to drill down to
i'm thinking like the compilation style
is like the stages
like running scenarios and predictions
but it's not as it's looking at all the
different flows through the program or
that's right yes
so one of the things that kind of hits
you in the face when you try to learn
rust is that suddenly you read something
and
jargon starts getting thrown at you some
of the jargon that we talk about is the
stack and the heap now the stack and the
heap are actually not data structures in
the classical sense you never see them
in your program but
the way that
a systems programming language like rust
deals with an unknown number of bytes
is through a process called dynamic
memory allocation
rust will
request more memory
from the operating system as it's
required that's why it's called dynamic
but there's a problem and that is it
doesn't know
where to put it at compile time so
instead
rust will allocate
the size of a pointer which is a memory
address so it's just a number it's
another integer and that integer
along with a length which is another
number so those are two things of fixed
size
will point to some other area of memory
that will be allocated by the operating
system at runtime we encounter a couple
of bits and pieces of jargon and one of
them is
unfortunately
named
term of like
a unsized type
and rast an unsized type is
a type that doesn't have a sort of a
complete known length let's say like a
string we don't actually know how a
string from some unknown source we don't
know how long it will be
but
some parts of it are known
and normally
the part set r will be a pointer
a
length and in the case of a string we
also retain the capacity which is how
many bytes we've actually allocated
with sort of there's a backing array as
well that we point to
now the cool thing i think about rust is
that you don't actually need to know
about pointers in order to make use of
the language
as your skills increase you can kind of
dig in and learn about them it's not
forced upon you
that's i think one of the reasons why
the rust community has kind of chosen to
say we are here to empower everyone it
sounds like
most of the effort is done at compile
time to figure out
what you've told russ that you might
need
but it also will figure out what it
needs so does that mean build time takes
longer than it would with another
language rust compile
times are relatively slower so it's in
some of its peer languages the rust
compiler is doing more work
it is tracking the use of all of these
variables
it turns out also that some of the
implementation details about how
the compilation steps work mean that
rust's
compilation model is slower but not for
the reasons around dynamic not for the
memory allocation thing
when we talk about blazingly fast that
obviously means runtime
because we've talked about the build
time
where would you see blazingly fast sit
in
you know with the rest of the language
ecosystem if rust is
pitched as a c plus replacement
and go is pitched as a
c replacement
does rush fit in somewhere between the
performance
stats of c and c plus or how do we put
some numbers against blazingly fast
that's what i'm trying to get to yeah
sure and that's a perfectly valid
question the rust community has put this
outrageous claim out so it's time for
for some evidence so i'm going to make a
another possibly outrageous claim and
that would be that i would find it
easier to write faster code in rust than
say c or c plus plus
and that is because a lot of the
abstractions are really ergonomic and
are very difficult to misuse whereas i
think i'd be anxious about my own
capability if i were to try and
re-implement something in
a language where i would have much more
manual control
rust provides you with the equal level
of manual control if you need it but
it's there for you so it's still
available whereas cnc plus plus in many
instances it's required that you
actually
do that so where does rust sit i'm
thinking of two main benchmarks there is
a site that used to at least been
maintained by the debian project called
the benchmarks game now this is a set of
a series of benchmarks which
consistently demonstrates that
rust is
on par with the highest level of
performance available so
rust
is
as fast as the fastest languages one of
the reasons why it's named rust is that
you
can't get closer to the middle
at least that's one of the slogans
the
other thing in terms of benchmarks
there is a web benchmark
one of the rust frameworks is able to
serve i think concurrently seven million
requests per
unit and i can't remember if the unit is
second or minute i believe it's actually
second which strikes me as a ridiculous
number of
requests yeah i need a big pot of
boundless to serve that
yeah you start saturating the the neck
there at that point
um yeah so
rust is consistently good one of the
other this is much more anecdotal than
those kind of two benchmark sites
but someone who i respect a lot his
name's brian cantrell he
has recently started with a couple of
co-founders the oxide computer company
and became notable as the creator of the
dtrace project for solaris
and
he has quite a fascinating blog post
where he says that you know like i've
been a c programmer for decades but my
rust is faster and that's because
it's just much easier to write fast code
and rust
that makes sense okay so one of the top
things
russ lists
as a major win is reliability
so let's take some time to explore that
what is a rich type system
a rich type system is a type system that
enables you to
express your intent really well that
helps with reliability because it can
optimize for that specific type and make
it more predictable or so rust does not
have exceptions its place it has this
notion of a result type a result a sort
of a placeholder value that can either
be
a successful return value or an error
case so we call this the ok or
error
now
if i return result from my
function signature so if i declared my
function as having result
then every caller that uses my function
must take account of the fact that it
could fail
it's impossible to compile a rust
program that hasn't included checking of
error cases it's simply not possible to
kind of skip over an error code that
would apply to
memory safety thread safety concurrency
anything absolutely the other type that
i i find like particularly
cunning really is the option so
rust encodes missing values with this
type that we'll call option and i think
haskell calls it optional so rust value
could be present we say it's there's
some value or it could be missing in
which we say there's none there
now this looks like each of those two
cases look as though they would take up
memory but it turns out that the none
case is completely invisible in the
final binary
it uses some really neat compile magic
to kind of prove to itself that it
actually never needs to represent none
in the actual binary itself because of
the fact that if something is present
then it will never be known it turns out
that this is a genuine zero cost
abstraction we have complete type safety
from the point of view that if something
takes an argument option it's impossible
to
work with that function and not take
account of the possibility that a value
may not be present so does that touch on
the ownership model guarantee
similar but different again so ownership
is another concept that gives you some
some of this reliability
and robustness but it works in a
slightly different way the optional case
though is is really just there to say
that
it's impossible to treat a function and
sort of silently hope that a value will
be present like none or some sort of nil
value or null depending on your
preference sort of turns up you're not
going to suddenly crash
or if i
carry on with some kind of erroneous
value
you
raise a very good point though this is a
kind of notion of an ownership or like
an owner that we haven't really
discussed in this conversation if
ownership
is tracked then you know who owns that
bit of memory and you know who owns that
bit of data that gets shared between
threads or you know things like that
absolutely the first thing to say about
ownership i think it's poorly named so
ownership
in a western mindset
implies that you are
able to
prevent trespassers from accessing
things that you own that is what
ownership means sort of the ability to
exclude others from access
it turns out that in rust the owner does
not have the ability to restrict other
parts of the program like no one comes
and checks for permission for the owner
it's impossible for the owner to ever
decline a request for
accessing the data that is owned the
owner only has one responsibility and
rust and that is to free the
or to delete
the value that is owned at the end of
its scope so if i own some integer at
the end of my lifetime i need to make
sure that integer has already been
deleted from memory turns out that this
is all implemented
with scopes and there's actually no
requirement for you as a programmer to
kind of call delete it just happens to
be the case that when my lifetime ends
that everything that i own
is also deleted
invent your future at caci a national
security company revolutionizing
technology through digital
c4isr
cyber space engineering and i.t
transformations
you'll deliver information dominance
through the development of next
generation solutions at caci you'll be
treated like the company's greatest
asset when a company believes their
people are their greatest asset they let
the best do what they do best
visit careers.caci.com
innovate to explore caci's engineering
and i.t opportunities
touched a little bit of this on the
introduction and something i want to ask
just now is about
the safety and ownership you've
mentioned there and the build time
length i'm just doing some c
work at the moment and i think part of
what you've described in the build
process where it looks at the safety
if you were to take c
and what we've just spoken about scope
i'm doing something where it opens a
socket a udp socket and then depending
on whether that's successful or not
and some other bits of memory
you return from the function
and the variables you've opened
behind the scenes of that variable some
memories opened go out of scope so it's
my job as a c programmer to understand
that that file descriptor takes some
stuff and leaves it open you know and
i've got to shut that down
now if i hadn't thought about that which
i didn't
i've got it this program plugged into
some static analysis tools like code ql
on github
clang analyzer and the coverty one that
checks for loads of different things and
see and it was only the coverty tool
that picked that up and said look here
online you know 57
you've opened up some stuff you've
checked the return code but the
variable's gone out of scope and you're
leaking memory
so
how i understood what you've described
just a minute ago in an introduction
all those third party things are all
scooped together and done at build time
with rust
you are correct so in terms of just rust
in terms of link opening closing sockets
or some resources
rust will kind of wind things down but
it's actually dependent on the library
itself that you know you might have some
udp library that knows about sockets one
thing that rust doesn't guarantee is
that your program will be free of memory
leaks so it is potentially perfectly
memory safe
to just leak memory if you know that
nothing will ever access that region
then rust will still compile it
if you were to kind of go under its back
and kind of re-implement some of the
functionality that's provided
in the standard library for example
and you wanted to be able to
rely on the fact that you're writing a
short-lived utility then you expect the
operating system will just clear
everything up when you're done because
it's only going to be
alive for 10 seconds
then
you can leak memory deliberately and
there isn't a check there memory safety
is more about
accessing memory that isn't yours
exactly rust will get very very
particular very stroppy with you and as
polite way as possible if you attempt to
access actually i'll be a little more
precise what i mean by access
multiple readers is fine
but there can only ever be one
place in your program that has right
access to any given value and rust
implements that without actually any
locking
so it can guarantee
in the most part that
exactly when it is safe to access values
and to modify them
without needing to
add extra locking mechanisms
now if you do wish to have a shared
variable
that is writers and multiple threads for
example you will actually be required to
place some form of locking or some sort
of synchronization mechanism in front of
that variable
but
in the single threaded case if we had
multiple references to some object only
one of them could ever have right access
does it figure that all out at build
time basically once you've got that
binary you know you're good once you
have your binary you're good the
but wait for the but
wait for that um
rust provides the ability for you to
call what we call unsafe functions
with an explicit unsafe block that is
clearly very very visible inside your
source code this is very common this
kind of pattern of we talked about c
just before if i want to import or sort
of link in a library that provides some
useful functionality say some
compression library
and it
requires a pointer and a length to the
bytes that it wants to compress
rust isn't able to provide any
guarantees at all about what the c
library does it doesn't have any way to
kind of introspect that library's
functionality and so there are some sort
of escape hatches to be able to
create raw pointers to do things that
are dangerous
you can cause crashes and unsafe rust
but you need to opt into that makes
sense there's an article i found on the
ieee computer society website which is
obviously what runs this podcast
called securing unsafe rust programs
with xrust
and they quote here rust is a promising
systems programming language that
embraces both high level memory safety
and low level resource manipulation
however the dark side of rust unsafe
rust leaves a large security hole as it
bypasses the rust type system in order
to support low level operations
recently several real-world memory
corruption vulnerabilities have been
discovered in rush shared libraries i
guess that's just where people have
flicked that switch to use the unsafe
rust and maybe not done right yeah it's
exceptionally difficult to do correctly
i give someone my gun with bullets you
know or not
i mean
yeah yeah right well gun with bullets
you know here's a loaded rifle please
treat it with respect
the other side of
rust for me just as someone who
has written a book for people who have
never done systems programming before
is that
i
often use the unsafe keyword examples
with inside that book because i want to
demonstrate how things are built
and it's quite fun actually to say oh
look here is a stream of bytes and they
are all you know one after the other but
actually i want to now treat them as an
array of integers and so we need to
actually take a series of four byte we
want to read in four bytes at a time and
just treat that in memory
as an integer and actually that's not
magical your cpu
does that all the time
and
i really appreciate that rust has
these escape hatches available for
people who do wish to kind of explore
and i've personally been really
impressed with this idea that
that rust actually kind of supports
people's intellectual curiosity so when
you're ready to do that and flick that
switch
you can look behind the curtain and see
what's going on that's right you can
also annotate your code with these kind
of forbid annotations to say that i
forbid the use of unsafe in this code
base you can actually decorate your
source code with these annotations which
actually look attributes some of these
attributes will refuse to compile your
code unless it complies with certain
style guidelines which is actually
surprisingly useful with things
relating to the same memory safety so
productivity for the developer
or for the team
what's the documentation like
pretty good and on the whole i think
there are areas that are spotty so
uh that's particularly in the sort of a
third-party ecosystem but i think in the
standard library the documentation is
excellent
the language itself is well documented
there is a free online book that you can
download
that's available to you that that
details entirely it's not as good as
your book though is it
well books are different right so mine
is intentionally different than other
material mine is about examples and
saying okay so you want to know let's
implement a cpu emulator let's implement
a database let's implement an ntp client
because i want to understand what ntp is
and timekeeping is and so my book is
really around
giving you the enough foundations of
rust so that you can actually manipulate
that and extend it whereas
the free work is
called the rust programming language
is really just we'll start at integers
and we'll walk our way through all the
way through the language and all of its
language features and then at the end we
will get to an example
what's a friendly compiler
a friendly compiler is one that provides
you with specific
errors that point you at the right place
it gives you a concrete reason why
something has broken and it gives you
suggestions for fixing it
and most of the time the suggestions are
very very
good
so rust is a friendly compiler in the
sense that every single error message
includes
a link to a web page that has
a very detailed explanation for what
this era is and why it is caused and how
to get out of it for me as someone who
had never really used a compiled
language before rust
i
am and did it heavily embedded to the
compiler team itself is the compiler the
same thing as a build tool is that all
in one
good point there's a small ecosystem of
tools that's a trio of tools that
comprise kind of the standard
tool chain sorry to throw more jargon
into the conversation so we have the
rust compiler so this is known as rust c
it is responsible for taking your source
code and taking the source code of all
of the dependencies
and massaging them into
an executable binary or a library
alongside that are two pieces of
software one of them we've talked about
called cargo
cargo is responsible for
downloading those dependencies kind of
re-arranging everything so that it's
easy for rust c to know where everything
is
and it also actually invokes rust c
itself so your day-to-day rust
programmer will typically run cargo
build
rather than interacting with rust c
directly
the third member of this trio is a hill
called rust up
and rust up is a tool that manages
tool chains and
you might say what's a tool chain
and the tool chain would be
whether or not for example you're
running
the stable rust compiler or you might
actually opt into the nightly compiler
which has kind of got more features but
actually comes with the possibility of
stability problems because things aren't
quite finished yet it also provides you
with the ability to install
a rust compiler for
other compile targets so you might be
running on windows but you want to
compile for linux or say you're you've
got rust on your macbook but you
actually want to compile for some other
target or your little microcontroller
and rust up manages all of that
excellent so we did a show on russ like
i said in 2017 is there a quick way to
say what's changed since then since your
chat with florian there have been two
rust additions a rust edition is an
opportunity for backwards incompatible
changes to be included to rust
notwithstanding that
if you opt into a new edition
your old code will actually still
continue to compile
and so rust's actually a very stable
language there were several changes made
in 2018. so would it just be a case of
looking up
what changed and applying that to your
code that's right the thing to search
for would be rust 2018 edition
in fact there is a
an addition guide as part of
the official documentation
and
the
2018 changes were created out of
playing with the language in anger for a
couple of years as an open source or
major open source project and it
simplified a lot of things which
actually added to the ergonomics
the 2021 edition kind of just adds even
just a tad extra polish it provides just
a couple of niceties for example the
ability for you to
have a conversion operation that may
fail so instead of it crashing on you it
returns a result which we actually
talked about a few minutes ago and just
a couple of syntactic niceties
that aren't available to
previous editions of rust and what do
you have to change
to use a newer version of rust is it the
tool chain or rust c or to opt into the
new version of rust every rust project
managed by cargo has a little metadata
file all you need is edition equals 2018
it's sort of like a little any file or a
little config file
if you're using quite a lot of libraries
from create to io
would it just be a case of doing the
usual thing where if one of those
doesn't work under 2021 you open a
ticket in that project and get up to
speed or should it always work you can
still include
third-party dependencies that themselves
are
using an older edition so you shouldn't
actually need to update any dependencies
to your compiler version today's
compiler can still compile code that was
in the original 2015 edition
so but if you want to contribute yes
raise the ticket and there shouldn't be
anything
that could compile that can't the
changes are mostly additive rather than
contradictory
how are these changes
proposed and discussed so the risk
community is quite special in the fact
that it has a very participatory
rfc or kind of request for comments
process
where
a change might be suggested in a
discussion forum which is then iterated
you know say oh that sounds like a
sensible you know people have a chat and
people might have a discussion and
decide that it's worth investigating
that will then be written up as a
proposal and then there are a couple of
teams and depending on which team
sort of sponsors the idea
then thanksgiving kind of move on from
there as well as additions rust has a
six weekly update cycle in terms of its
minor version updates and so
if something is not backwards
incompatible or you're not trying to
create something that the an old
compiler won't understand then quite
often you can include substantive
changes
inside one of those six-week cycles
and if you were trying to keep up to
date with that would you just keep an
eye on the announcements and rebuild
your binary
or when do you do that do you just leave
it running wherever it is deployed or do
you just build that into your deployment
type thing
no this i think is actually quite an
important misconception to kind of
squish if we can
the language does have a minor update
every six weeks
but
the stability is still there your code
will still continue to compile
and
no backwards incompatible changes are
made in the newer versions you kind of
get new fancy things you know you can
opt into that okay what does the future
look like for us since the whole mozilla
foundation creation
my view is that rust's future is
extremely strong
rust continues to grow exponentially in
terms of its adoption it's receiving a
lot of attention as we said with these
marquee companies but actually what i'm
really intrigued by or really hopeful
for
is that smaller kind of maybe
lesser-known companies might be taking
it on for sort of side projects and for
kind of exploratory work
and
that to me is
where i think a lot of the growth will
be people are excited that it has been
the
developers most loved programming
language for the last six years in a row
but if you can't actually work with it
day to day then it doesn't mean a lot
and what i'm hopeful for is that the
ecosystem will continue to
to really encourage creativity and
really encourage people who are willing
or interested in learning excellent
thank you obviously rust is a very
powerful language with a strong
ecosystem
but if there is one thing that a
software engineer should remember from
our show what would you like that to be
the one thing that i would like people
listening to
take away is that
is that they can learn rust
that they can share in its advantages
don't be put off by the fact that you
that you've heard that it's difficult to
learn there are more resources there are
different resources available you don't
need to follow the same path as everyone
else
excellent
invent your future at caci a national
security company revolutionizing
technology through digital
c4isr
cyber space engineering and i.t
transformations
you'll deliver information dominance
through the development of next
generation solutions at caci you'll be
treated like the company's greatest
asset when a company believes their
people are their greatest asset they let
the best do what they do best
visit careers.caci.com
innovate to explore caci's engineering
and i.t opportunities
so tim one thing i didn't ask in the
fallout question was how does rust run
without an operating system you
mentioned that in the introduction
this is called running code on bare
metal and
it
involves compiling your binary to
something that can be kind of triggered
with the bios and
this is something that's actually
supported by rust sort of out of the box
so where can people find out more if
you'd like to learn more about rust i
think a good place is rush dashlang.org
me i'm tim clicks is what i normally go
by so that's um
t-i-m-c-l-i-c-k-s
perfect and i've got a link for the rush
one edition
and the benchmarks you gave me thank you
very much hey that's my pleasure it's
been a real pleasure and this is gavin
henry for software engineering radio
thank you for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at
se-radio.net provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin facebook twitter
or through our slack channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening